

#### **SUMMARY**

17 years plus of experience in Information Technologies. Professionally certified: OCP, CHA, CHP, CHI, CTT+, CIW, MOS, ITIL, CISSP and CEH. I see opportunities in challenges. Strong background in designing and developing training strategies and implementing security solutions. My instructional background provides me the tools to communicate effectively and translate complex technological topics into understandable pieces of information.

My philosophy of teaching is open and flexible but undoubtedly adhering to high standards. I have learned through my students ways to improve my teaching and I look forward to develop innovative ways to reach my students. It is my compromise to go above and beyond to help you learn, understand and apply database management courses. You will be treated as an IT professional and as such I will present you with challenges every opportunity I have. Although you are in a couched environment I will expect from you to behave as a professional, the best professional that you can be. Have no fear of condemnation in my classes; my classes are a place to learn.

# SELECTED SKILLS

- Expertise in: ISO17999, computer security practices, RDBMS design and management, Ethical Hacking and Countermeasures, HIPAA, ITIL, Linux Administration, Oracle Databases, Web Site Design and Development, Search engine optimization and marketing and RSS.
- Expertise in: web-based instruction / training, computer mediated communication, course/training design and development, CAI and interactive multimedia, distance education, evaluation of instructional systems, instructional design and development, job, task and content analysis, management of instructional development projects, web-based assessment, test instruments and instructional systems design.
- Excellent adaptability with multicultural, diverse and international environments. Excellent interpersonal skills and the ability to work with a team as well as independently.
- Experience collecting, analyzing, and reporting qualitative and quantitative data as well as advanced knowledge of statistics, evaluation, assessment, and research design.
- Experience planning, designing, development, and audit of Information Protection Projects, Business Continuity and Disaster Recovery Plans and Security Reviews including the strategic development of security architectures, policies and procedures in accordance with ISO 17799.

COMPUTER. MULTIMEDIA and INTERNET EXPERTISE (Both Windows and MAC OS)

Hypermedia/Authoring Interactive Teaching Learning

Graphics/Image Manipulation

Distance learning, Groupware

Digital Video/CD Technology

**Desktop Publishing** Office, Grant Crafts

Research

**Programming** 

Languages/Technologies

**Operating Systems** 

Web Authoring and Design

Databases/Systems Security Related

Toolbook, Icon Author, Designer's Edge.

Macromedia Director, Authorware, Flash.

Photoshop, InDesign, Illustrator, Canvas, CorelDraw, PaintShop Pro.

WebCT, Blackboard, Net Meeting, Moodle, Aulanet, **Topclass** 

Adobe Premier, Digital Cameras/Boards, Corel.

Acrobat, PageMaker/Photoshop, MS Publisher.

MS Office, File Maker, MacProject, MS Project.

Statistical Analysis Systems: SAS, SPSS, Minitab, Infopoll.

BASIC, Clipper, HTML, XML, JavaScript.

DOS/ Windows, UNIX, MacOS, Novell.

PageMill, FrontPage, Expression Web, Dreamweaver, IIS Administration and deployment.

Access, Paradox, Oracle, Peoplesoft and MYSQL.

Nessus, NMAP, Knoppixx STD, HonetNet, SNORT

Syracuse, NY. US



# EDUCATION & TRAINING

Doctorate Degree: (ABD) Instructional Design, Development and Evaluation.

Concentration: Distance Education and Web based training.

12, 2003 School of Education, Syracuse University. Syracuse, NY. US

Professional: Paradox, Advanced SAS, PeopleSoft Financials-HR-ST, Brioquery, Authorware,

HTML, FrontPage, DNS, data sharing, and Relational Database Design.

1997-2000 Syracuse University.

Master's Degree: Instructional Design, Development and Evaluation. Concentration: Evaluation

and Research.

12, 1997 School of Education, Syracuse University. Syracuse, NY. US

Bachelor's Degree: Licentiate in Integral Education. Major in Mathematics.

06, 1995 Simon Rodriguez University (UNESR). Caracas, DF. VEN

Certification: Certified Ethical Hacker

07, 2007 ECCOUNCIL NY, NY. US

**Certification:** Certified Information Systems Security Professional CISSP

08, 2005 ISC<sup>2</sup> NY, NY. US

**Certification:** ITIL Fundamental (EXIN)

06, 2005 Syracuse University Syracuse, NY. US

Certification: Oracle 9i Database Administrator

06, 2005 Syracuse University Syracuse, NY. US

Certification: CompTIA CTT+ (written part, pending video)

09, 2003 Syracuse University Syracuse, NY. US

Certification: CompTIA i-Net+

09, 2003 Syracuse University Syracuse, NY. US

Certification: CIW Associate

09, 2003 Syracuse University Syracuse, NY. US

**Certification:** Certified HIPAA Instructor, HIPAA Administrator and Professional

01, 2003 HIPAA ACADEMY Syracuse, NY. US

Certification: Oracle 8i Certified Professional Database Administrator

09, 2002 Oracle Syracuse, NY. US

Certification: Help Desk Analyst Certified Instructor

09, 2002 Help Desk Institute Syracuse, NY. US

**Certification:** Train the Trainer

08, 2001 Langevin Syracuse, NY. US

Certification: 25 creative ways to add excitement to your training

08, 2001 Langevin Syracuse, NY. US

Certification: Microsoft Master Instructor MOUS

2001 Microsoft Syracuse, NY. US

Certification: Microsoft Office User Specialist: Outlook

2001 Microsoft Syracuse, NY. US

Certification: Microsoft Office User Specialist: PowerPoint

2001 Microsoft Syracuse, NY. US

Certification: Computer Systems Security Auditor.

12, 1994 National Institute for Educational Cooperation. San Juan, GU. VEN

**Certification:** Hardware Maintenance of Computer Systems.

6, 1994 National Institute for Educational Cooperation. San Juan, GU. VEN

**Certification:** Software Troubleshooting of Computer Systems.

2, 1994 National Institute for Educational Cooperation. San Juan, GU. VEN



# PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE (some)

#### **Computer Tech Instructor**

2001-Present Center for Business and Information Technologies.

Syracuse, NY. US

As a Senior Computer Technology Instructor my activities include, but are not limited to delivering specific training curriculum on a variety of topics surrounding the Help Desk industry, Oracle Database Technologies, IBM DB2 Technologies, ITIL, HIPAA, Network+, Security+, Microsoft Certified Desktop Support Technician, Network Defense and Countermeasures, Network Security, Certified Ethical Hacking, Certified Information Security Specialist Professional and Microsoft Office Applications within the CNY market (both at SU facilities and at the facilities of corporate clients). I am involved in all aspects of the design, development and evaluation of courses/programs by providing technical expertise and intellectual content for CBIT- developed courses, recommend and supplement purchased materials for licensed (externally developed) courses. In average I delivered more than 540 hours of instructor-led training per year. In addition I am involved in assessing potential opportunities for new courses/programs, developing course outlines, requirements, testing, and evaluating the courses/programs. Responsible for Security strategy, policy, technical and administrative procedures. I also specialize in security hardening and management technologies, overseeing architecture and implementations successfully from the ground up. My primary focus is developing security integration frameworks & security testing tools to provide defense in depth towards security assurance. I manage Oracle databases and web servers to provide my students a 24/7 availability lab environment. I also manage a learning management system based on Moodle to complement face-to-face instruction and to provide online support. I also serve as the webmaster for: CBIT, Outsourcing Professional Institute and others.

#### **Computer Based Assessment Specialist**

2002-Present <u>WebPortalSolution.</u>

Syracuse, NY. US

- Oracle consulting,
- IT security consulting/auditing, SOX, HIPAA, ISO17799, Penetration Testing, Ethical Hacking
- Oracle Database Tuning,
- Customization of open-source portal solutions.

#### **Computer Based Assessment Specialist**

1998-2001 Office of Residence Life - Syracuse University.

Syracuse, NY. US

- Responsible for collecting, analyzing and reporting quantitative and qualitative data including SAS advanced programming for data analysis. Designed, developed, and implemented campus-wide web-based surveys. Security strategy, deployment and auditing. Responsible for securing 1 public subnet and 2 servers. Responsible for Security strategy, policy, technical and administrative procedures.
- Designed, developed and implemented the strategy for the adoption of an innovative Webbased assessment tool for data collection and reporting. Designed and developed databases with web-based interfaces. Co-managed twelve annual research projects.
- Performed strategic and implementation planning, security certification and accreditations, security test and evaluation, risk management, and technology assessments to in the areas of communications, networking, operating systems, applications, security, messaging, and wireless.
- Designed, developed and conducted numerous hands-on coaching/training sessions for professional and para-professional staff: Effective Web-based research, Basic copyright and fair use guidelines, Assessment, Testing, Professional presentations, Focus group methodology, Survey design, Research methods, Analyzing and reporting quantitative and qualitative data, University policy on human rights under research, ethical consideration in research, Infopoll, Summarizing data with excel, Brioquery, Listserv Managing, Document Analysis, and Participant Observation techniques.
- Instructional developer, web based training, CBT, job-aids, and technical manuals.



## Lead Designer, Java code / HTML developer.

1997-1997 OCM-BOCES Regional Information Center.

Syracuse, NY. US

- Front-End-Analysis on organizational requirements and practices.
- Responsible for organizational assistance, research design, HTML, and JAVA implementation, consultation, and development of advanced web structures.
- Navigational and hierarchical system design and development.
- Project Management, team coordination, intra-departmental liaison, and training of personnel in the creation of departmental pages.
- Responsible for Security strategy, policy, technical and administrative procedures.

# **Training/Organizational Consultant.**

1994-1996 <u>Electrónica de Computación C&V C.A.</u>

Maracay, ARA. VEN

- Consulted, analyzed designed, developed and implemented the training of clients.
- Provided critical strategic planning, team building, staff management and implementation skills.
- Authored, co-authored and administered training products, multimedia training and job-aids design.
- Designed and implemented corporate team culture, personnel training and time management.
- Developed training and provided coaching to staff.
- Worked with content area specialists on the selection and implementation of the appropriate learning strategies and delivery technologies to design, develop and evaluate digital courses and curricula.
- Identified and implemented appropriate learning strategies and delivery technologies to meet the needs of target student/trainee populations for each project.
- Evaluated and used appropriate technologies for the development and delivery of instructional materials and strategies.
- Trained/coached trainers in course material design/production and in the effective use of course materials in the classroom as well as in computer-based courses.
- <u>Types of industries served</u>: Construction, Health Care, Universities, Non-profit organizations, Small Private companies, Banking/Financing, and Industry.
- Among clients: Universidad Romulo Gallegos, Gobernación del Estado Guárico, Asamblea Legislativa, Constructora Lud-Villa, Servicentro Cagua, Facultad de Odontología, and Unidad Pediatrica San Sebastian.
- <u>Training Topics</u>: Computer desktop applications, Basic of Networking, Emergency Procedures, Customer Service, Job Standard Procedures, Proprietary Software Training, Software Troubleshooting, and Corporate Culture.

## **PUBLICATIONS**

- Villalba, Carlos. (1998) Current and Ideal Practices in Evaluating Multifunctional Software Programs that Support Web Based Instruction, Chicago IL.
- Villalba, C., (1998), Investigative Inquiry Using the Internet: Evaluating Internet information sources., Proceedings of the 12st Annual Dr. Kelly's Evaluation Conference, Ottawa -Canada. February 11.
- Villalba, C. (1998). Instructional design basis for faculty. Proceedings of the IInd Educational Technologies for Distance Education, Higher Education and Libraries Symposium. Merida - Venezuela. July 8-11.
- Chamberlain, A., Jang, S., Morgan, J., Villalba, C. (1998). Cultural Influences on Emergent Evaluation Designs. In Smith, N.L. (chair), Research on Evaluation: SIG/Survey Research in Education. Interactive Symposium conducted at the Annual Meeting of the AERA, Montreal, 1998.
- Villalba, C. & Romiszowski, A. (1999). AulaNet and other Web-based Learning Environments: a comparative study in an International context. Proceedings of the 1999 ABED International Conference, Rio de Janeiro, August 1999. São Paulo, Brazil: Associação Brasileira de Educação a Distância (ABED). www.abed.org.br
- Villalba, C. & Romiszowski, A. (2000. Structural Communication. Proceedings of Teaching



- Tools. Syracuse University, Syracuse, NY. [2000 October].
- Villalba, C. & Romiszowski, A. (2000). Structural Communication and web based instruction.
  Proceedings of the World Conference on Educational Multimedia, Hypermedia, and
  Telecommunications. [CD-ROM]. AACE, Montreal, CA. [2000, June 28th].
- Villalba, C., & Romiszowski, A. J. (2001). Current and ideal practices in designing, developing, and delivering Web-based training. In B. H. Khan (Ed.), Web-based training. Englewood Cliffs, NJ: Educational Technology Publications.
- Villalba Carlos. (2003).Distance Education in Venezuela. Brazilian Review of Open and Distance Learning, 2(3). Available online at www.abed.org.br
- Villalba Carlos. (2004).Structural Communication and Web Based Instruction. Brazilian Review of Open and Distance Learning, 2(4). Available online at www.abed.org.br
- Villalba, C. & Romiszowski, A. (2004). Structural Communication and web based instruction.
  Series on Computer Science and Applications. in V. Uskov.WEB-BASED EDUCATION,
  Calgary, AB Canada. 646 pages.
- Villalba, C. & Romiszowski, A. (2004). Structural Communication and Web based Instruction.
  Presented at and published in the proceedings of the IASTED International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Applications (AIA 2004), Innsbruck, Austria, 16-18 February 2004.
   416-128
- Villalba, C. (2005). How It Works: Oracle Database Security. Secure Enterprise Magazine. http://www.nwc.securitypipeline.com/howto/57701821. February 2005. US.
- Villalba, C. (2006). Network Defense and Countermeasures. Manufacturing Association of Central New York. April 2006. US.
- Villalba, C. (2006). Securing the corporate environment. Manufacturing Association of Central New York. Nov 2006. US.
- Villalba, C. (2007). Securing IT. Association for Computing Machinery. June 2007. US.
- Villalba, C. (2007). HIPAA Security Rules. NYTechSummit-2007. June 2008. US.
- Villalba, C. (2008). Disaster Recovery Planning. Manufacturing Association of Central New York. Feb 2008. US.
- Villalba, C. (2008). Securing Electronic Records: HIPAA Security. NYTechSummit-2008. June 2008. US.

Assisted in the publication of more than 16 independent trade titles.

Authored and published seven instructional seminars, and self-help booklets.

Authored and published two books.

Assisted in peer-reviewed publications as editor.

## **AWARDS**

- SUIQ Certificate of Exemplary Achievement, Chancellor's citation. Syracuse University. 2000.
- Vice President's award for outstanding graduate student. Syracuse University. 2000.
- Who's who in American Universities & Colleges. Syracuse University. 2000.
- Honorable mention for the "DIVERSITY" core award. Office of Residence Life. Syracuse University. 2000.
- Honorable Member of the Phi Beta Delta, Honor Society for International Scholars. 2003
- US Department of Labor. Defining the Workforce (Collaborator) 2007.

#### **AFFILIATIONS**

- Association for the Advancement of Computing in Education. (Member)
- American Evaluation Research Association. (Member)
- Venezuelan Organization of Students & Scholars. (Treasurer)
- Review of Education at a Distance (Editor). http://www.abed.org.br
- Center for International Services (Editor). <a href="http://sumweb.syr.edu/lescis">http://sumweb.syr.edu/lescis</a>
- Brazilian Association for Distance Education (Editorial Board)
- IBM Scholars Program (Member)

# **WORKING LANGUAGES**

- Spanish (native),
- English (fluent), translation (written and verbal),

700 University Av Suite 203, Syracuse, NY 13244.

🖀 (315) 443-2914 | 🖳 <u>cavallal@syr.edu</u>





Portuguese (fair verbal).